A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Operations, Vice President, Office Files of John Colborn FA1377
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Operations, Vice President, Office Files of John Colborn
1984-2013
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Colborn, John
FA1377
4.94 Cubic Feet 13 document boxes: 13 letter size boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in four accessions between 2020 and 2023 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2020:027, 2021:139, 2022:054, 2023:053.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files John Colborn created when he worked at the Ford Foundation. Files are included from Colborn's positions in the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS) Economic Development unit, Office of Program Management, and Operations. Colborn was a Program Officer and then Deputy Director of the ASSETS Economic Development unit, Director of Program Operations in the Office of Program Management, and then finished at the Foundation as Vice President of Operations.
The collection is comprised of two series. Subject files documenting Colborn's management of the ASSETS Economic Development unit's workforce development portfolio and his later program strategy work as Operations Vice President are contained in the first series. The second series contains notebooks Colborn created when he served as Operations Vice President.
The bulk of the collection's materials concern the Community College Bridges to Opportunities Initiative (CCBOI), a joint project by ASSETS and the Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) that was tied to Colborn's workforce development programming. CCBOI and other components of Colborn's work focused on building career pathways, adult learning, low wage workers, skills training, education reform, and state policy for community colleges.
Common material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, meeting materials, notes, drafts, reports, proposals, memos, articles, and publications.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of two series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible. Notebooks in series 2 were arranged by date.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1984-2011
Series 2. John Colborn notebooks, 2010-2013
Ford Foundation; Adult education; Adult education and state; Community colleges; Economic development; Educational change; Training
- Subject files, 1984-2011; 1; 3.99 Cubic Feet 10.5 document boxes: 10.5 letter size boxes
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains the subject files John Colborn created and maintained when he worked at the Ford Foundation. Most of the files regard Colborn's work as a Program Officer and later Deputy Director of the Asset Building and Community Development Program (ASSETS), Economic Development unit. A few files show how Colborn continued to support some of the projects he started in the Economic Development unit when he transitioned to become Director of Program Operations in the Office of Program Management. There are some materials at the end of the series that Colborn created when he served as Vice President of Operations at the Foundation.
  Colborn's activities in the Economic Development unit focused on workforce development. Drafts, copies, and materials related to Colborn's Assignment Memo, Program Officer Memo, Reflection Memos, and Exit/Transition Memo describe the purpose, scope, and progress of his workforce development portfolio. The Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) and the Sectoral Workforce Development Initiative were two of the main projects of Colborn's workforce development programming.
  Most of the files in the series concern the CCBOI. There are files regarding CCBOI meetings, grantees, and evaluations. Other records document the planning of the initiative and its evolution from the Workforce Education Development Initiative (WEDI) and regard grantmaking for community colleges through groups like the Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP).
  The files Colborn created as Vice President of Operations generally concern the program strategy of the Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) and a Fiscal Year 2011 strategic review for the program.
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Summer 2008 Meeting, New York City, New York (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Winter 2005 Meeting, Santa Fe, New Mexico, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Summer 2004 Meeting, New York City, New York (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Fall 2004 Management Meeting (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Winter 2004 Meeting, New Orleans, Louisiana, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Summer 2003 Meeting, Seattle, Washington (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Fall 2003 Management Meeting, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Winter 2003 Meeting, New York City, New York, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Summer 2002 Meeting, Salt Lake City, Utah (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bridges to Opportunities Initiative - Center for Workforce Success Business Champions Initiative, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Winter 2008 Meeting, Washington D.C., 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Fall 2007 Management Meeting (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Summer 2007 Meeting, Chicago, Illinois, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Summer 2006 Meeting, Cincinnati, Ohio, 2003-2006 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) March 2007 Management Meeting (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) March 2008 Management Meeting, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Winter 2007 Meeting, San Francisco, California, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) October 2006 Management Meeting (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) outline and development, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) planning phase - Consultant proposals, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) planning phase - Site selection, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) March 2005 Consultants Meeting (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) evaluation - Renewal proposal, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Budget and administration, 2001-2005 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) pre-2004 materials, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) - Community Colleges Funders February 2004 Meeting, New York City, New York, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) - Community Colleges Funders Summer 2004 Meeting, Indianapolis, Indiana (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) - Community Colleges Funders September 2004 Meeting, San Francisco, California (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) June 2005 Meeting (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) - Grantmakers for Education (GFE) October 2005 Meeting, New York City, New York, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) May 2006 Meeting, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative Career Pathways Toolkit, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Open for research. Digital access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Community College Affinity Partnership (CCAP) June 2007 Meeting, New York City, New York (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) October 2005 Consultant Team Meeting (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
  - Projects of the Community College Leadership Program University of Texas at Austin - Using State Data to Improve Community College Student Success and Attainment January 2006 Meeting, San Antonio, Texas, 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Breaking Through Peer Learning Meeting, April 2007, Portland, Oregon, 2003-2007 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - American Association of Community Colleges (AACC), 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - California Tomorrow, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Campaign for College Opportunity, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Colorado Community College System (CCCS), 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Council for the Advancement of Adult Literacy (CAAL), 2004 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Douglas Gould and Company, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) - Douglas Gould and Company, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Kentucky site - Kentucky Community and Technical College System (KCTCS), 1998-2004 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Ohio site, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - KnowledgeWorks Foundation, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
  - John Colborn and Cyrus Driver June 2005 visit to Louisiana Community and Technical College System (LCTCS) (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Louisiana Community and Technical College System (LCTCS), 2003 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity (CCBOI) Louisiana site - Louisiana Community and Technical College System (LCTCS), 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Community College Bridger to Opportunity (CCBOI) - Low-Income Families Empowerment through Education (LIFETIME), 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC), 2000-2002 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) Opening Doors, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) Opening Doors - February 2004 meeting visit to Kingsborough Community College, 2003-2004 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) Opening Doors, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) Opening Doors, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Manpower Inc. and Abt Associates, 2000-2002 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (MDRC) Opening Doors February 2005 Conference Leadership Dinner at Ford Foundation, 2004-2005 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Assignment Memo for workforce development, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - California Focus Groups, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Ford Foundation workforce development history, 1984-1999 (Box 6, Folder 63-64)
  - Aspen Institute Future of Sector Meeting, May 2004, Washington D.C. (Box 7, Folder 65)
  - Aspen Institute Sector Research Meeting, April 2004, Washington D.C. (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Educated Workforce Initiative (EWI), 1998-2002 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Workforce Development Program Officer Memo development, 1998-1999 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Workforce Development Program Officer Memo - Reconnaissance of the workforce development team, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Workforce Development Program Officer Memo - California Focus Groups, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Workforce Development 2001 Reflection Memo, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Workforce Development 2001 Reflection Memo - Transforming State Workforce Development Systems (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Workforce Development 2002 Reflection Memo, 2002 September 30 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Workforce Development 2003 Reflection Memo, 2001-2003 (Box 8, Folder 74)
  - Workforce Development 2004 Reflection Memo (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - John Colborn 2006 Exit/Transition Memo - Workforce Development (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Workforce Development portfolio initiatives and grantees - Miscellaneous, 2005-2006 (Box 8, Folder 77-78)
  - Workforce Education and Development Initiative (WEDI) - Focus groups, 1998-2000 (Box 9, Folder 79-80)
  - Evaluation of Ford Foundation's Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI), 2003-2005 (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Washington site - State Board for Community College Education, circa 2002 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Colorado site - State Board for Community Colleges and Occupational Education (SBCCOE) Foundation, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) Colorado site - State Board for Community Colleges and Occupational Education (SBCCOE) Foundation, 2003-2004 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) New Mexico site - New Mexico Association of Community Colleges (NMACC), 2003-2005 (Box 9, Folder 85-86)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) New Mexico site - New Mexico Association of Community Colleges (NMACC), 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - John Colborn 2006 Exit/Transition Memo, 2006 July 31 (Box 10, Folder 88-89)
  - Community College Bridges to Opportunity Initiative (CCBOI) evaluation - Interim report, Community College Research Center (CCRC), 2004 (Box 10, Folder 90-91)
  - Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) 2011 Presentations (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Philanthropy reference materials with John Colborn notes, 2003-2004 (Box 10, Folder 93)
  - Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) Units Fiscal Year 2011 program strategy, 2008-2011 (Box 11, Folder 94)
  - Economic Opportunity and Assets Program (EOA) 2011 Strategic Review summary, Lindsay Steinmetz (Box 11, Folder 95)
  - Cost Reduction Consultation Process, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 96)
- John Colborn notebooks, 2010-2013; 2; .95 Cubic Feet 2.5 document boxes: 2.5 letter size boxes
  The series contains 13 notebooks John Colborn created through his activities working at the Ford Foundation. The notebooks do not have labels describing the dates they cover. Date information was gathered and inferred from the content of the notebooks. Colborn used these notebooks when he served as Vice President of Operations at the Foundation from 2010 to 2013.
  Colborn used the notebooks for meetings and program strategy. A few other items were inserted into the notebooks like other notes and business cards. The notebooks were arranged by date during processing.
  - 2010-2011 notebook, circa 2010 September-2011 January (Box 11, Folder 97)
  - 2011 notebook, circa 2011 February-March (Box 11, Folder 98)
  - 2011 notebook, circa 2011 April-May (Box 11, Folder 99)
  - 2011 notebook, circa 2011 June (Box 12, Folder 100)
  - 2011 notebook, circa 2011 October (Box 12, Folder 101)
  - 2011-2012 notebook, circa 2011 December-2012 January (Box 12, Folder 102)
  - 2012 notebook, circa 2012 March-April (Box 12, Folder 103)
  - 2012 notebook, circa 2012 June (Box 12, Folder 104)
  - 2012 notebook, circa 2012 July-August (Box 12, Folder 105)
  - 2012 notebook, circa 2012 September-October (Box 13, Folder 106)
  - 2012-2013 notebook, circa 2012 October-2013 February (Box 13, Folder 107)
  - 2013 notebook, circa 2013 February-April (Box 13, Folder 108)
  - 2013 notebook, circa 2013 May-June (Box 13, Folder 109)